<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of a Protestant gentleman in Ireland to a late letter from N. N. upon a late discourse between them concerning the present posture of that countrey, and the part fit for those concerned there, to act in it.</title>
            <author>Protestant gentleman in Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176289</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13289934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13289934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 444:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of a Protestant gentleman in Ireland to a late letter from N. N. upon a late discourse between them concerning the present posture of that countrey, and the part fit for those concerned there, to act in it.</title>
                  <author>Protestant gentleman in Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[MDCLXXXIX] 1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>N. N.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER OF A <hi>Proteſtant Gentleman</hi> IN IRELAND, TO A Late LETTER from <hi>N. N.</hi> Upon a late DISCOURSE between Them concerning the preſent Poſture of <hi>That Countrey,</hi> and the Part fit for Thoſe concerned There, to Act in it.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church Yard.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98829:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98829:2"/>
            <head>THE ANSWER OF A Proteſtant Gentleman in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE you cannot <hi>help it,</hi> but are puſht on by a fatal Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, I will not wonder that you add ſo ſcurrilous a Letter to ſo inſipid a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Notions that have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled your Head,</hi> had evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that Noddle that firſt conceived them, I apprehend no Damage could have accrued to me by the Diſappointment: and you might with ſafety have appeaſed the Twinges of your tender <hi>Conſcience,</hi> without diſcovering ſo little regard to common Honeſty. I am obliged to you, for the Liberty you give me, to <hi>make what uſe of them I pleaſe;</hi> the Choice is eaſily deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd, I know what
<hi>uſe to make</hi> of waſte Paper. But I crave leave to diſagree with your Judgment;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98829:3"/> ſince I cannot underſtand your Arguments ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, or your Deſign ſo ingenious, <hi>To put me in the right way te keep my Eſtate in</hi> Ireland however you cajole me with a complemental Acknowledgment of a <hi>former Welcome there.</hi> As you need not tell me
<hi>the Danger it is in;</hi> ſo there is no neceſſity to delude me with improper Directions, how to eſcape it; wiſhing that the way were <hi>plainly ſeen,</hi> and yet plainly wiſhing that I may not <hi>take it.</hi> When you pretend <hi>to be plainer,</hi> you appear to me to be moſt intricate; for what can you mean by <hi>the two pretending Kings to</hi> Ireland? Certainly, it muſt be <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Lewis;</hi> and I am fully ſatisfied, that which ſoever of thoſe two <hi>ſides</hi> I take, I <hi>take the unjuſt ſide,</hi> and really deſerve to loſe my Eſtate. Your <hi>Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> has no more Influence on me, than your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and tho with a Jeſuitical Equivocation, you flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Proteſtant Intereſt, yet ſecretly and ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly you promote the Popiſh Intrigue.</p>
            <p>I might turn the <hi>Point</hi> upon you and retort your own Words, <hi>[I do not ingage in the Point of Right and Wrong between King</hi> James, <hi>and King</hi> William, <hi>which of thoſe has the beſt Title to this Crown; or rather, which has a Title, and which has not;]</hi> but your Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is ſo foul, ſo malapert, ſo impudent, that it cannot be repeated without the danger of Infection. For who but a profligate Wretch, caſe-hardned with a Popiſh Zeal, and Superſtition, durſt belch out ſo uncharitable a Cenſure on thoſe glorious Adventurers who
<hi>contributed</hi> to the miraculous reſtitution and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhment of the Proteſtant Religion under a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant King and Queen? But now the Vizor is off, it is no longer Popery in maſquerade, the Jeſuit is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98829:3"/> bare-faced; no man, but one trained in that diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Diſcipline, would preſume to aſperſe the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Actors in the late Settlement, with thoſe odious Terms of
<hi>Falſeneſs, Weakneſs, and Baſeneſs;</hi> and ſo profanely ſcoff at a
<hi>Reformation of the Lord's doing.</hi> Were there any other Advantage to be gain'd by the Wager, than your <hi>yielding that whole Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be lawful and juſt;</hi> I could as poſitively lay my Bett, That the <hi>firſt Contrivers and Promoters of it</hi> were principally guided by a Care and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment for the Eſtabliſhed Religion, and not ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to it by thoſe diſ-ingenious Motives of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Advantage, or Ambition:</hi> But ſo bold and baſe an Aſſertion, ſo contrary to Truth, Senſe, and Experience <hi>[that Religion is in a worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, than it could have been put by King</hi> James <hi>as long as he could have lived]</hi> deſerves no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but a Whip and a Scourge: ſo ſawcy and virulent an Expreſſion
<hi>[that the whole Proceeding is the blackeſt and fouleſt that ever ſhewed its Face in the World, not excepting that againſt King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt]</hi> is not to be anſwered with Patience. Nevertheleſs, I will for once play the Stoick, and calmly reaſon the Caſe with you. Either you groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly equivocate, or you ſpeak nothing to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; if by <hi>Religion you mean your own, and the Popiſh Perſuaſion, it is very palpable that it is in a worſe condition, than King</hi> James <hi>would have put it:</hi> if you mean the Proteſtant Religion, how can you with that Confidence aver it to be <hi>in a worſe condition?</hi> Are the Biſhops impriſon'd, indicted, and try'd for Actions merely moral, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious? Are the Heads and Members of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98829:4"/> arbitrarily turn'd out, and the Fountains of Learning tainted by Romiſh Poyſon? Are any Sort or Party of Proteſtants diſcountenanced? Are Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments Civil and Military taken from men, becauſe they will not truckle to the Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Popiſh Council, or ſtiſle the Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a good Conſcience, by the proſpect of a good Place? Are there any Popiſh Chappels open, or Jeſuitical Schools and Seminaries permitted in the Land? Does the King brow-beat his Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents for not following him to the Maſs? or the Miniſters of State make the Roman Catholick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion the End and Pledge of your Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Do the Court-Agitators put a Muzzle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Reaſon, or infringe your natural Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Free-will? Or have you been Cloſeted, and obliged to give your Vote againſt the Dictates of your Judgment? Is there a Maſs openly celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Kingdom, a Jeſuit to be found, or a Fryer to be ſeen? If not, how ridiculous is the Compariſon? How ſenſeleſs the Preſage? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion is now become the National and Univerſal Profeſſion, cheriſhed by the King, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the Parliament; in the late Reign it was clouded, deſpiſed, and rendred altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſhionable, and in all probability would have been quite extinguiſhed, if <hi>James,</hi> your King, had long li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo. And now let us conſider the Circumſtances of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, and his Apoſtate Son; and look into the Parallel of their ſeveral Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. The one of an Angelick Life, the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Goodneſs, and Mirror of Virtue; who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Saint, and dyed a Confeſſor; it will be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98829:4"/> undecent to reflect upon the Immoralities of a Prince; turn the end of the Perſpective, and all conſiderate Men will agree in the Character of the other. The one indeed was <hi>accuſed openly,</hi> Things laid to his Charge that he knew not, perſecuted and deſerted by the predominant Party of his Subjects, and cut off by a Form of Law and Juſtice: the other had his Accuſation legibly ſtampt on all his Actions, by the Breach of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the eluding of Oaths, and the Infraction, or Suſpenſion of the Municipal Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; he affronted and caſt off his beſt and trueſt Subjects, he deſerted the Throne, and by a ſpontaneous Act <hi>Abdicated</hi> the Government; he was neither impriſoned nor reſtrained, but by his Flight he juſtly incurs the Guilt of thoſe Crimes which an inward Witneſs confronted him with, and which the Modeſty as well as Prudence of the Government has forborn to make publick, ſince it is not the Cuſtom of <hi>England</hi> to try and condemn the abſent, or to execute men in Effigie: and if ſuch men <hi>[whom he hath raiſed from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and done ſuch ſingular kindneſs to]</hi> prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Religion and the Salvation of their Souls, before the ſervile Compliance with an Idolatrous Worſhip, and ſupporting the Tyranny of a Bigot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Zealot, and Inflexible Votary to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> in my Opinion they deſerve to be placed in the firſt Rank of good Patriots and Champions for the Liberty and Proſperity of their Countrey. And if the Government be ſo tender of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of an Abdicated Prince, as not to publiſh what they know concerning the <hi>ſuſpected Birth of the Prince of Wales; the Secret League with</hi> France, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98829:5"/> let it not be imputed to <hi>ſham</hi> or Defect of Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; do not dare or defy them to do ſuch a thing, leſt that may fall out, which has often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to an inſulting and unprovoked Challenger. Your Similies about <hi>ſetting Fire to a Part of the Houſe,</hi> may paſs for very Elegant; but let me retort the Allegory, and ask you, what ſay you to him, that ſets Fire to the whole Houſe, and <hi>runs away</hi> by the Light of it? For <hi>ſuch Papers as are writ on this Subject,</hi> I willingly remit you to hug your ſelf in the Delight you take in them, and intreat you at the next Edition, to affix to them your
<hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let us joyn Iſſue; let us (to uſe your Metaphor) open the Tables, and try the ſeveral <hi>Games</hi> that are <hi>to be Play'd;</hi> or to humour your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, let us take out the Dice, and either play at In and In <hi>with one of the Kings; or at</hi> Hazard, <hi>if the contrary ſide ſhould prevail.</hi> Moſt Judicious Sir! I do admire your Logical Head, which way you could find out ſuch extraordinary Remarks, as have eſcaped the Curioſity of others! You begin Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically, you conclude Dogmatically, and you proceed all the way Fallaciouſly.
<hi>If the Proteſtants of</hi> Ireland <hi>ſide with King</hi> James, <hi>and King</hi> William
<hi>prevail, how can you be certain that King</hi> Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <hi>cannot make them ſuffer with any face of Law, Equity, Conſcience or Policy?</hi> To me it appears quite otherwiſe; for tho you beg the queſtion in your Parentheſis, and poſitively pronounce that King <hi>James</hi> has not <hi>Abdicated the Government of</hi> Ireland; all Men that know the Conſtitution of that Kingdom, and its ſubordinate Dependance upon <hi>England,</hi> will ſpit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98829:5"/> Contradictions in your face, and inform the World, that when the Parliament of
<hi>England</hi> have declared the Throne vacant, and placed the Regal Diadem on King
<hi>William,</hi> it will neither be againſt Law, nor Equity, to puniſh ſuch perſons as voluntarily and wittingly adhere to King <hi>James,</hi> with loſs of life, and Confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Eſtates. Neither is the caſe the ſame as was in <hi>England,</hi> ſo long as King
<hi>James</hi> was actually King, no man was blamed for ſerving under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, nor obnoxious to Puniſhment for being faithful to him; but when he is actually <hi>deprived of his Regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and had abandon'd the Government, when King</hi> Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <hi>is in Poſſeſſion of the Throne, and publickly proclaimed both in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>according to your Poſition, Law, Equity, and Conſcience, are of the ſide of the lawful King</hi> (i. e. <hi>of him whom the Legiſlative Power of the Land has conſtituted King) at leaſt as long as he is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph you have conjured up a Spirit, which with all your skill you cannot exorciſe; you have ſtarted an Objection, which with all your Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry you cannot anſwer. The Right and Power of <hi>England</hi> in and over the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> is unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, no King of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Conqueſt of it, ever went into
<hi>Ireland</hi> to be Crowned; but by the aſſumption of the Crown here, he is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come King there. Certainly if you were converſant in the Hiſtory and Laws of
<hi>Ireland,</hi> you would never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe the World with ſuch frivolous queſtions. You would know that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige <hi>Ireland</hi> by an Act incluſive, that by ſpecial words the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> may bind the Subjects of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, vid. Cook.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 350. That Appeals are made from thence to the Parliament here; that the Privy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98829:6"/> Council can ſummon Offenders before them, that the Judges of the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> can remand the Hearing of Cauſes by Writs of Error. Nay, the Parliament of
<hi>Ireland</hi> are ſo ſubjected to the Power of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Poyning</hi>'s Law, made in the Tenth of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, that they have not the power of an ordinary Grand-Jury in making Preſentments, a Bill cannot be brought into the Houſe, before it is approved <hi>by the Council in England,</hi> and Inrolled in the Chancery there; ſo that if the
<hi>Parliament in</hi> England <hi>cannot lay a Tax upon the Eſtates in</hi> Ireland (which for the Honour of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, I will neither determine nor diſpute) yet it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent by all Hiſtories and Records, they may do things of a higher nature, and ſettle the Throne of
<hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by an Authority paramount to theirs; (tho it has been uſual to make a Recognition of the Regal Title in that Kingdom in their proper Parliament, in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and concurrence with what is done in this) and the ſame indubitably will be practiced, whenſoever King <hi>William</hi> ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the Poſſeſſion of that forlorn Country.</p>
            <p>You cavil and <hi>banter,</hi> when you <hi>ſet the Convention</hi> againſt the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> againſt <hi>King William.</hi> The Lord Keeper has the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as the Lord Chancellor, tho not ſo great a Title; the
<hi>Convention</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> are different terms, one <hi>Latin,</hi> the other
<hi>French;</hi> but their Power and Juriſdiction the ſame. When we ſay, the Three Eſtates convened in Parliament, is not the Convention in the Parliament, and the Parliament
<hi>conſiſting of the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Three Eſtates? There muſt be no long
<hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy in the Throne,</hi> the King never dies, but upon the Natural, or Civil Death, or departure of the Regnant Prince, the Throne muſt be immediately fill'd, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98829:6"/> when the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> is ſolemnly proclaimed, and placed in the Throne, and Crowned King; he is a Rebel and a Traytor that queſtions his Right, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth his Government.</p>
            <p>You reer the Fabrick of your Diſcourſe upon a falſe foundation, you gull the people by a ſubdolous Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>That King James is lawfully poſſeſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of</hi> Ireland. You may as well be an Advocate for the <hi>French</hi> King, and aſſert his Right to
<hi>Alſatia, Lorrain,</hi> and many Towns in <hi>Flanders,</hi> becauſe he is poſſeſt of them by force; you may as well plead for his Brother the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> and juſtifie his Uſurpation of all the Chriſtian Territories. About <hi>November</hi> laſt you might have ſaid ſuch things without controul: He was then the Regnant King, and tho by his Religion he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to hold the Reins of Government, yet before Conviction and Sentence, no man taxed his Diſability; tho by his Violation of Oaths, Subverſion of the Laws, and Arbitrary Intruſion on the Subjects Properties, be juſtly forfeited his right to rule; yet no man reſiſted him. But now when out of a ſecret Guilt he hath withdrawn himſelf, and without compulſion abdicated the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when the Legiſlative Power hath exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and dethroned him, and have actually placed the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and its dependant <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon the head of another; he that will own <hi>James</hi> to be ſtill the King, deſerves to be exploded at
<hi>Newgate,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed at <hi>Tyburn.</hi> But if King <hi>James</hi> ſhould prevail, and keep the poſſeſſion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (whereof by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous diſſimulation of his Deputy <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and the aſſiſtance of his <hi>French</hi> Myrmidons, he has already too great a ſhare) it is eaſie to <hi>ſee how it is likely to fare with thoſe who pretend to ſet up King</hi> William, and if they muſt claim <hi>no better Title or Security for their Lives and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98829:7"/> Eſtates, than what they muſt be obliged to his mercy and kindneſs for,</hi> the conſequence is obvious; it will prove the Tranſcript of the horrible Perſecutions in <hi>France</hi> (far tranſcending all thoſe of the Heathen Emperors put together) the <hi>Dragoons</hi> will tread the Stage, and react thoſe Tragical Barbarities on the Scene of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Can we expect any other Anſwer or Uſage than the Proteſtants of
<hi>Suffolk</hi> received from Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> whom they placed on the Throne, when the Papiſts had ſet up the Lady <hi>Jane Grey?</hi> Or any other return than the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant hath made to his Subjects of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, for eſtabliſhing his Title againſt all other Pretenders? Conſider the Proceedings of the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, and then tell me if any man in his ſenſes ought to relie on the Word and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a Popiſh Prince made to his Heretical Subjects. He was famous under the advantageous Characters of Piety, Probity, Vertue, a zealous Son of the Holy Church: His Proteſtant Subjects continued faithful to him, and did not adhere to King <hi>Frederick,</hi> tho a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince, and choſen King by the States of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia;</hi> yet when he became Maſter of the Country by his Victory at <hi>Prague,</hi> he handled them with equal cruelty and ſeverity, as thoſe who had ſided with <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> only he allow'd them this hard choice, either to change their Religion within three Months, or to depart the Kingdom: Nay, when he had ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and ſworn to obſerve the Articles agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> in favour of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> (many of whom had ſerved in that Army which reduced
<hi>Bohemia</hi> to his Obedience) yet ſo ſoon as he ſaw himſelf in a condition to need no more of their ſervice, he was abſolved from the obligation of his Promiſes by the Biſhop of
<hi>Averſa,</hi> and thereupon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98829:7"/> they were all baniſh'd, as well as the moſt obnoxious. And by the way obſerve, the Proteſtant profeſſion was the eſtabliſhed Religion of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as firmly ſettled as Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Edicts could make it, no leſs publickly profeſt and generally ſettled in that Kingdom, than it was in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> notwithſtanding within a few years the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion was wholly extinguiſh'd, by the Violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made on their Laws, Liberty, and Property, by this pious Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, contrary to all ſolemn Engagements, Promiſes, and publick Faith.</p>
            <p>The reſt of your Argument will prove a trifle, if the matter be ſtated right, you inſiſt upon the Diſpute between King <hi>William</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> but take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him that ſits behind the Curtain, that when the Gameſters have try'd their luck, intends to ſweep away the Stakes. If King <hi>James</hi> retain his Uſurped Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, it is but to be Tributary to the <hi>French</hi> King, and what muſt the Proteſtants expect under his Protection, but Rapes, Robberies, Murders, and utter deſolation, and deſtruction? <hi>If King</hi> William <hi>prevail and recover Ireland,</hi> (as well we may hope, ſince God is on his ſide) Reaſon and Juſtice will incline him to call them to account, who have abetted the
<hi>Iriſh French</hi> Intereſt, and then perhaps your <hi>Terra firma</hi> will be ſhaken, and you may look for a Repriſal in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> or <hi>New Atlantis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not to be wonder'd at that you who were wont to ridicule the Popiſh Plot, ſhould pretend a disbelief of the intended Maſſacre in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Thoſe whom you call
<hi>timerous</hi> and <hi>unthinking people,</hi> had more wit than to believe themſelves in ſafety under a Popiſh Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they withdrew their perſons and their effects in time, while many thouſands of credulous men, cheated by the ſpecious pretences, and horrible Imprecations of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> (never true to his word, but in his appointed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98829:8"/> days to Aſſault and ruin the Proreſtants) and amuſed by the miſtaken policy of the through paced profeſſors of Religion; continued there, till they were driven to the pinching <hi>Dilemma,</hi> of Complying or Starving. And <hi>now, in the Name of God,</hi> why ſhou'd any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Man doubt the deſign of the Papiſts to <hi>inſlave the Britiſh,</hi> to <hi>deſtroy the Religion,</hi> and utterly to extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the
<hi>Proteſtants,</hi> either gradually, or by an univerſal <hi>Maſſacre?</hi> Why were Arms ſecretly bought up, and an unuſual Furniture of Chain-Bridles provided by ſome of the Iriſh Clergy? Why was <hi>London-Derry</hi> to be poſſeſſed by a multitude of Highlanders and Papiſts on the 7th. of <hi>December</hi> laſt, but in order to that bloody Deſign to be perpetrated on the 9th. Did not <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> about that time give Commiſſions (only upon a bare Letter from his Maſter) to raiſe 40000 Men, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above 50000 Arms? Were not the New Officers to maintain their Troops and Companies by ſuch a proportion of Beef, Mutton, and Meal for Three Months; and did they not raiſe that ſupply by Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Britiſh? Were not the Proteſtants in <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> plunder'd? The whole Province of <hi>Canaght</hi> pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laged? All Arms and Horſes forcibly taken from the Inhabitants of <hi>Dublin</hi> and forty Miles round it? Is not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> (who upon the News of the Barbarous proceedings in the other Provinces Arm'd and got together for their ſelf Defence) almoſt totally over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run by the inſulting Enemy, their Houſes and Eſtates taken from them, their Tenants begger'd, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves forced to ſeek a Refuge in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> Have not many Proteſtants been Murther'd, ſome by Rage, and ſome by a Form of Law? Have not others been cheated by the Trick of Protections, while the Officers defend them from the Rapine of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98829:8"/> the Army, but expoſe them to the Fury of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? <hi>May not any Man of common ſenſe, the moſt Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in all</hi> Ireland, <hi>plainly ſee</hi> (to retort your own Words) <hi>the Maſſacring the Engliſh</hi> would make Room for the French, and unite all Papiſts under the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of King <hi>Lewis? And if ſo, can any Man</hi> with Reaſon condemn thoſe that have eſcaped from <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or adviſe thoſe that remain there to juſtifie, and ſupport the Brace of Uſurpers.</p>
            <p>Hitherto you have vented your Spleen, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd many undecent Reflections on the King and Parliament; but now you Attacque us with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentile Exprobation of our preſent Neceſſities. Tho' our <hi>Rents</hi> do not <hi>come out of</hi> Ireland <hi>after us,</hi> but are intercepted by ſuch as have no Right to them; yet we may live, the generous people of
<hi>England</hi> will not let us ſtarve, we are not in the leaſt doubt but <hi>King William</hi> will <hi>provide handſom ſubſiſtence for us,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our ſeveral Capacities. We are proud that ſo Illuſtrious a perſon as <hi>my Lord Hallyfax</hi> will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe <hi>to ſolicite for us,</hi> and hope it will be to better purpoſe, than the Negotiation of Father <hi>Peters,</hi> or my Lord <hi>Powis</hi> Sollicitation for you. If
<hi>Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Hamilton</hi> has neglected his Honour and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and contributed to the deſtruction of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men; I hope Monſieur <hi>d'Avaux</hi> will Reward him according to his merits. For my part I do intend <hi>to ſpend my time in</hi> London, till the Kings Commands oblige me to be elſewhere, and I do not fear that it ſhall ever be in the power of
<hi>King</hi> James <hi>to puniſh me</hi> for it. And however you reproach and upbraid us with
<hi>Hunger and Want,</hi> I can aſſure you, your Friends in <hi>Ireland,</hi> are in no great plenty of <hi>Meat and Drink:</hi> Hunger and Poverty are the concomitants of King <hi>James</hi> his Court,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98829:9"/> tho' it may be better endured by his French Control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and his Iriſh Followers, who never were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to fuller Feeding.</p>
            <p>Your next is a meer Wheadle; but be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Proteſtants here <hi>have no mind to return</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> while either French, <hi>or Iriſh are Predominant;</hi> neither will they <hi>ſeek a Licenſe from King</hi> James <hi>to ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> here,</hi> or his <hi>Pardon</hi> for their <hi>Abſence.</hi> But when King <hi>William</hi> ſhall imploy them, they hope to return, and call them to account, who have occaſion'd their Exile.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider <hi>the Caſe,</hi> which you have ſtated with all poſſible Art, Malice, and falſe Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Your deſign is to inſtill a Jealouſie into the minds of the Proteſtants, to foment a miſtruſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Engliſh and Dutch,</hi> and by a ſide-blow to wound the Honour of our Gracious King. It is not impoſſible, but <hi>King James</hi> may for ſome time <hi>keep the poſſeſſion of</hi> Ireland for the uſe of King <hi>Lewis,</hi> and may <hi>Seize and Poſſeſs himſelf</hi> (but not <hi>fairly) of my Eſtate:</hi> It is no leſs poſſible <hi>that King</hi> William may after ſome time
<hi>beat out King</hi> James, and his French Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, <hi>and ſettle himſelf intirely in that Dominion.</hi> Well, what then: Muſt my Eſtate be liable to Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture becauſe it was Seized, and Uſurped by proclaimed Rebels? Is there any Colour of Senſe or Reaſon to ſtart a compariſon in the Caſe between <hi>Britiſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> forced to forſake the Country, and abandon their Eſtates for ſafety of their Lives in the Reign of <hi>King William,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> who unprovoked, in the time of Peace and Quiet; took up Arms, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd ſo many Thouſands of their Fellow-Subjects, who by King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt and his Parliament, were declared <hi>Traytors</hi> attainted by the Law, their <hi>Eſtates Forfeited by Rebellion;</hi> and veſted in King
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98829:9"/> Charles <hi>the Second at his Reſtauration?</hi> Such an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be urged only by that ſort of Men, who with a ſeared Conſcience and a brazen Impudence, deny the Gun-Powder Treaſon; make a mock of the Horrid Popiſh Plot, and juſtifie the former damnable Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as an undertaking for Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And what if the King have an Inclination to gratifie <hi>Monſieur B—g,</hi> and thoſe other Worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who have faithfully ſerved him, and aſſiſted in the Expulſion of Tyranny, Popery, and Arbitrary Government, and ſecuring the Peace and Religion of the Kingdom? Is there any neceſſity to make the Proteſtant Eſtates the Reward of their Service? No there are Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> to the value of 300000. <hi>l. per annum</hi> belonging to <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, (now in Actual Rebellion againſt the Crown of <hi>England</hi>) with which the King may amply Recompenſe his Servants, and diſtribute his Favours according to their reſpective Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. In the mean time, King <hi>William</hi> being a Man of exemplary Piety, exalted Virtue, univerſal Probity, and the Champion of the Proteſtant Religion, I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſtruſt his Juſtice, nor doubt his Generoſity; I reſt ſecure and ſatisfi'd that he will in time reſtore me to my former Eſtate, and give me more, if by my Service I can deſerve it.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion which you Propoſe, and pretend to Anſwer, carrys the Confutation in the very Terms of ſtating it: you ſay, in caſe we ſhould return to that which perhaps is juſtly enough called our Duty, ſo as to reſtore King <hi>J.</hi> to his Right and Crown again, how ſhall we be aſſured we ſhall not fall under the ſame dangers we apprehended our ſelves before both in our Religion and Properties. He can give no better nor other aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, than publick and ſolemn Promiſes added to ſuch Acts of Parliament as we ſhall contrive and frame for our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98829:10"/> own Security.— Have we not had all theſe already, and has He not broke them all? Does not his pretended <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power</hi> at once ſet aſide all Promiſes, Laws, and every thing but his Will and Pleaſure? And though He ſhould now diſclaim That to get in again, will it not be very eaſie when He is in, to lay hold on that common, and indeed many times juſtifiable come off of Kings, that He was then under a force, and could not bind himſelf to His own wrong, or to the diminution of His Prerogative. I confeſs here is a hard queſtion, and that which makes it harder yet, I am afraid the Charge againſt us is moſt of it true, therefore I ſhall ſhorten my Reply, and only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate in Brief: If a Prince placed in the Throne by the dint of Loyalty, Fidelity, and Love to his Family, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued from the Bill of Excluſion, Eſtabliſhed in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by the Generous and Unanimous adherence of his Parliament, and the Deſtruction of the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> Careſs'd with dutiful Addreſſes and joyful Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, enriched with Conſiderable Additions to his Revenue, Complemented with a Connivance at the Private Exerciſe of his Religion, and adventuring the Security of ours on the bare Aſſurance of his Word: If ſuch a Prince under ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Glory and Felicity, beloved by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and dreaded by Foreigners, would tamely ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelf to be impoſed on by Prieſts and Jeſuits, diſhonour himſelf by an Embaſſy to <hi>Rome,</hi> Provoke his People by ſetting up Maſs-houſes, and Popiſh Seminaries, Invade Mens Properties, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw ſome Laws, and Diſpence with others; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the Heads of Colleges, Impriſon the Biſhops, diſcard all Men from Civil and Military Imployments, that refuſed to Worſhip the Image which he had ſet up; endeavour by Threats and Promiſes to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch his Servants, and by ungenerous Arts to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98829:10"/> his Subjects, to break down the Bars that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Proteſtant Profeſſion; What muſt we expect if by the Indignation of God he be Re-eſtabliſht on the Throne; certainly he can never aſcend thoſe Steps, but ſupported by the Papiſts, and trampling on the Necks of Proteſtants; Rage, Revenge, blind Zeal, Ignorant Devotion, Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Service, the Purchaſe of Heaven, the eſcape of Purgatory, the Popes Bulls, the Jeſuits Tricks, the Prieſts Prayers, and the pernicious Advice of Popiſh Councellors, will tranſport him beyond all Senſe of Honour, and precipitate him into Actions Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and imitating, if not exceeding the Inhumane Cannibals in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I grow weary now of this Expoſtulation, and I am amazed to ſee any Man obtrude ſuch Chimerical crude Notions, ſuch fallacious Equivocating Argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuch thred-bare Repetitions, upon Men that can Read, Obſerve, and Underſtand. <hi>If King</hi> James <hi>have not a mind to get upon his Throne again by the Power of his</hi> Iriſh <hi>Army,</hi> What made him go there? Why has he raiſed ſo many Men, carryed over ſo many Arms, diſarm'd and deſtroy'd the Proteſtants, and Summon'd a Parliament; and though <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Strength of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland (by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God) ſhall ever be too hard for them, yet it is not impoſſible but the Popiſh Party (ſeconded by the Atheiſtical Crue, and ſuch as, being alway diſguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the preſent Government, are gaping for an Alteration, they know not to what) may ruffle and diſcompoſe the Calm Serenity <hi>Great Britain</hi> is bleſt with, and become the Setters and Fore-runners of a <hi>French</hi> Invaſion. And that ſurely we have great Reaſon to expect, (notwithſtanding the many <hi>Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties you ſeem to object,</hi> but do not believe) ſince
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98829:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>French</hi> King has been at ſo great Charge and Hazard to Comfort and Reinforce his inconſiderable Allies there; for whoſoever knows the Monarch of
<hi>France,</hi> will not ſuſpect him to be ſo mean Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as to be Compaſſionate, or ſo Impolitick to waſt his Treaſure, and expoſe his Forces, to Re-eſtabliſh an exil'd and forlorn Prince: I am more than confident he will not diſſemble ſo groſs a Self-denial, but intends to turn the Mortgage of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into a Fee-ſimple, and by the Livery and Seiſin already given him in part, to claim, and ſeize the whole. And than (as you ſay)
<hi>King</hi> Lewis <hi>would get more by the Victory than King</hi> James, <hi>and it would do King</hi> James <hi>little Service to have the Kingdom ſo recovered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Prophetick Suppoſition (that <hi>the People of</hi> England <hi>may bring themſelves to be Conquer'd by</hi> France) ſhall be no more regarded, than your ſlye Inſinuations, to induce them to ſo ſervile a Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or your tacite Commination, that ſuch a
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> is <hi>approaching,</hi> or your Pernicious Proſpect of ſo unpracticable an Accommodation, that the <hi>People of</hi> England <hi>ſhould conſent to receive King</hi> James, <hi>without any fear of ſuffering by him, either in their Religion, Laws, or Properties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Concluſion is agreeable to the Premiſes, <hi>a diſingenious Reflection on the People of</hi> England, who in all Ages have manifeſted a Prudential <hi>care of themſelves,</hi> and at this Juncture will do it, maugre your Crafty Inſinuation to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Upon the Word of a Gentleman, I do aſſure you, <hi>I do not take it ill that you have offer'd your Thoughts,</hi> which how wild and Incongruous ſoever, can have no other Influence upon me, than to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me to <hi>Continue,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
